<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Giacomo's Blog</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Giacomo's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 17:35:55 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SLAP: Succinct Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments from Standard Assumptions</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/slap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 17:35:55 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/slap/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This blog-post is a short introduction to our new work: &amp;ldquo;SLAP: Succinct Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments from Standard Assumptions&amp;rdquo;. This is joint work with Martin Albrecht, Oleksandra Lapiha and Ngoc Khanh Nguyen, and the full version is &lt;a class="link" href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2023/1469" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>available on eprint&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In our &lt;a class="link" href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/" >previous paper&lt;/a>, me and Khanh looked at the problem of constructing efficient lattice-based polynomial commitments, to be used in as a drop-in replacement to non-post-quantum secure schemes such as KZG.
In doing so we constructed two schemes making use of the techniques in [WW23]&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> to obtain succinct verification and extractability. The schemes that we came up two came with a number of caveats namely:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>a common reference string of quadratic size in the degree of the polynomial to commit&lt;/li>
&lt;li>reliance on a non-standard assumption: powerBASIS.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>one of our schemes achieves polylogarithmic verification time, but has non-negligible (inverse polynomial) soundness error.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the other scheme instead has negligible soundness error, but only quasi-polylogarithmic verification time.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In this work, we address all of these issues and obtain a lattice-based polynomial commitment scheme with:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>polylogarithmic common reference string size&lt;/li>
&lt;li>quasi-linear commitment time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>polylogarithmic verification time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>negligible soundness error (without parallel repetition)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>security that reduces to the hardness of Module-SIS, a standard lattice assumption.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="roadmap">Roadmap&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Refer to the &lt;a class="link" href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/" >previous blog post&lt;/a> for a refresher on polynomial commitment schemes and more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Construction of a polynomial commitment scheme is a two-step process:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Construction of a commitment scheme&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Designing of a proof system for the statement &amp;ldquo;$f(u) = z$ and $\mathbf{t}$ is a commitment to $f$&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>We take a brief look at both of these steps.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="merkle-prisis-commitment">Merkle-PRISIS commitment&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In order to achieve succinct verification, we require that the first commitment is &lt;em>compressing&lt;/em>. Further, we would like the scheme to be binding for &lt;em>arbitrary&lt;/em> vectors in $\mathcal{R}_q$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our starting point is a &amp;ldquo;toy&amp;rdquo; 2-to-1 commitment scheme. Below, for some fixed $w, \mathbf{A}$, and denoting by $\mathbf{G}$ the &amp;ldquo;gadget matrix&amp;rdquo; let
$$
\mathbf{B} = \begin{bmatrix} \mathbf{A} &amp;amp; &amp;amp; - \mathbf{G} \\ &amp;amp; w\mathbf{A}&amp;amp; -\mathbf{G} \end{bmatrix} \enspace.
$$&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Setup}(1^\lambda) \to (\mathsf{pk}, \mathsf{vk})$ samples $\mathbf{A}, w$ and uses [MP12]&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> sampling to construct a trapdoor $\mathbf{T}$ of $\mathbf{B}$. The verification key consists of $\mathbf{A}, \mathbf{W}$ and the proving key additionally contains $\mathbf{T}$.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Com}(\mathsf{pk}, f_0, f_1) \to (\sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ sets $\mathbf{t}_b := f_b \cdot \mathbf{e}_1$. It then uses $\mathbf{T}$ to sample short $\mathbf{s}_0, \mathbf{s}_1$ and $\hat{\mathbf{t}}$ such that $\mathbf{B}[\mathbf{s}_0, \mathbf{s}_1, \hat{\mathbf{t}}]^\top = [-\mathbf{t}_0, -\mathbf{t}_1]^\top$, it then outputs $\mathbf{t} := \mathbf{G}\hat{\mathbf{t}}$ and $(\mathbf{s}_b)_b$ as decommitment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, f, \sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ checks that the openings are indeed short, and that the equations are all satisfied: namely it checks that, for $b \in \{0,1\}$, $$w^b \mathbf{A}\mathbf{s}_b + \mathbf{t} = \mathbf{t}_b \enspace.$$&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>This scheme is binding under a 2-arity version of the PRISIS assumption introduced in our previous work, which we had shown to Module-SIS!
With this observation, the natural next step is to use this &amp;ldquo;toy&amp;rdquo; scheme recursively, and construct a &amp;ldquo;Merkle tree&amp;rdquo;-like structure.
To do so, we sample a matrix and a trapdoor for &lt;em>each layer&lt;/em> of the tree, and commit to the commitments originating for the bottom layer. Note that this achieves already the efficiency goals that we had set for ourselves, as building a Merkle tree only requires a linear number of invokations of the inner commitment scheme.
Does this overall scheme satisfy the binding property? Well, in fact if you look at the commitment that is used in the inner nodes of the tree, that is &lt;em>not&lt;/em> by itself binding. However, we show that the overall construction is binding under a multi-instance version of the PRISIS assumption of arity 2!
We then provide a reduction of this multi-instance assumption to the single instance version, which combined with our previous observation reduces binding to Module-SIS. We further show a direct tighter reduction from multi-instance arity 2 PRISIS to Module-SIS, which we use for parameters later on.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="evaluation-protocol">Evaluation protocol&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The evaluation protocol that we design is conceptually very similar to the one that we developed in our previous work. We take inspiration from FRI and Bulletproofs. In each round of the protocol, the prover splits the polynomial in $2^k$ components (when $k=1$, components correspond to the odd and even coefficients). It sends evaluations of these polynomials and &lt;em>partial opening&lt;/em> corresponding to the $k$-th layer of the tree.
and receives randomness from the verifier, that it uses to compute a new polynomial, of degree roughly $d/2^k$, that corresponds to the random linear combination of those components. Prover and verifier then can efficiently update the common reference string, instance and witness and recurse on the claim.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By itself, this protocol achieves polylogarithmic verifier and communication complexity, but inherits many of the drawbacks of the previous protocol, namely the inverse polynomial soundness error. To improve, while avoiding parallel repetition, we make use of the techniques of [BHRRS21]&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, combined with the amortization techniques that we had talked about in our previous work. Our new protocol (as our old) has efficient proof aggregation, in the sense that proving many statements of the form $\{ f_i(u) = z_i \}_{i \in [r]}$ has cost roughly equivalent to proving a single claim. To amplify soundness, we prove the same claim multiple times, and use the aggregation techniques in order to mantain efficiency. An appropriate setting of parameters then enables us to have an evaluation protocol that has polylogarithmic verifier and communication complexity, and negligible knowledge soundness error.
In particular, this means that we can compile the protocol to a non-interactive argument using the Fiat-Shamir transform, and achieve a sound non-interactive polynomial commitment scheme with polylogarithmic proof sizes, common reference string, and quasi-linear time prover.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The scheme here presented is for proving evaluations of polynomials over polynomial rings, while most uses of polynomial commitments in the wild are concerned with finite fields. While we could make use of the techniques in the previous work to obtain such a scheme, we also present a new generic transformation that could be of independent interest.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="instantiations">Instantiations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We performed an evaluation of the concrete efficiency of our scheme, details of which you can find in the full version. Concretely, proof sizes for a polynomial of degree $d = 2^{20}$ are around 36 MB, which makes the scheme concretely inefficient. Some of these inefficiencies are inherent in the [MP12]&lt;sup id="fnref1:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> trapdoor sampling techniques that we make use of, some from the high number of repetitions that our techniques require. Reaching concrete efficiency is left for, ambitious, future work.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>H. Wee and D. J. Wu. &amp;ldquo;Succinct Vector, Polynomial, and Functional Commitments from Lattices&amp;rdquo;. In: EUROCRYPT (3). Vol. 14006. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Full version: &lt;a class="link" href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/1515" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/1515&lt;/a>. Springer, 2023, pp. 385–416.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>D. Micciancio and C. Peikert. &amp;ldquo;Trapdoors for Lattices: Simpler, Tighter, Faster, Smaller&amp;rdquo;. In: EUROCRYPT. 2012, pp. 700–718.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref1:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>Alexander R. Block, Justin Holmgren, Alon Rosen, Ron D. Rothblum, and Pratik Soni. &amp;ldquo;Time and Space-Efficient Arguments from Groups of Unknown Order&amp;rdquo;. In: CRYPTO 2021. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Heidelberg, 2021, pp. 123–152.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments: Towards Asymptotic and Concrete Efficiency</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 20:49:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this blog-post, I will be taking a look at my recent work with Ngoc Khanh Nguyen, &lt;a class="link" href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2023/846" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>full version&lt;/a>.
We extend the vector commitment scheme of [WW23]&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> with an evaluation proof, and achieve a lattice-based polynomial commitment scheme with polylogarithmic proof size and verifier complexity.
We further investigate the applicability of our techniques to the Polynomial IOP of [Marlin]&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, show that our scheme is easily batchable and more!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="polynomial-commitments">Polynomial Commitments&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A polynomial commitment scheme is a natural generalization of a vector commitment scheme, in which a party is able to commit to a polynomial $f$, and later engage in a &lt;em>evaluation protocol&lt;/em> to show that $f(u) = z$. In this work, we consider polynomials of bounded degree $d$ with coefficients over the polynomial ring $\mathcal{R}_q$ (we also show to adapt this construction for polynomials in $\mathbb{F}^{\leq d}[X]$, but details are left for the full version).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The interface of a polynomial commitment scheme follows partially that of standard commitmentscheme:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Setup}(1^\lambda) \to (\mathsf{pk}, \mathsf{vk})$ takes a security parameter and outputs a proving and a verification key.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Com}(\mathsf{pk}, f) \to (\sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ takes a proving key and a polynomial $f$ and outputs a commitment $\sigma$ and auxiliary decommitment information $\mathsf{aux}$.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, f, \sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ checks whether $(\sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ are a valid commitment-opening pair for $f$.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Furthermore, we extend the interface with an evaluation protocol between a prover and a verifier $\mathbf{P}, \mathbf{V}$. We denote the protocol as $\langle \mathbf{P}(\mathsf{pk}, f, \mathsf{aux}), \mathbf{V}(\mathsf{vk}) \rangle(\sigma, u, v)$.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The properties that we require from a polynomial commitment scheme are:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Completeness of the commitment scheme: If $\mathsf{pk}, \mathsf{vk}, \sigma, \mathsf{aux} $ are honestly generated (w.r.t to $f$), then $\mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, f, \sigma, \mathsf{aux}) = 1$.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Binding of the commitment scheme: The probability that an efficient adversary can find $\sigma, f,g, \mathsf{aux}_f, \mathsf{aux_g}$ such that $\mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, f, \sigma, \mathsf{aux}_f) = 1 = \mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, g, \sigma, \mathsf{aux}_g)$ is negligible.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Evaluation completeness: If $f(u) = z$, the evaluation protocol will accept.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Evaluation knowledge-soundness: There exists an efficient extractor that, if a malicous prover is able to make the verifier accept with non-negligible probability, is able to extract a polynomial $f$ and an opening $\mathsf{aux}$ such that $f(u) = z$ and $\mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, f, \sigma, \mathsf{aux}_f) = 1$.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>In the paper, we also consider hiding, but in the interest of space we avoid this here.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="weewu-commitments">WeeWu Commitments&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Our starting point is the commitment scheme introduced in [WW23]&lt;sup id="fnref1:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Their commitments relies on the BASIS assumption (Basis-Augmented Short Integer Solution). It roughly states that an adversary that is given access to a random matrix $\mathbf{A}$, should not be able to find a short vector $\mathbf{v}$ such that $\mathbf{A}\mathbf{v} = 0$ even when given access to a trapdoor to sample short preimages of a matrix $\mathbf{B}$ related to $\mathbf{A}$. In their work, the matrix $\mathbf{B}$ is defined as $$\begin{bmatrix}\mathbf{A}_0 &amp;amp;&amp;amp;&amp;amp; - \mathbf{G}\\ &amp;amp; \ddots &amp;amp; &amp;amp; \\ &amp;amp; &amp;amp; \mathbf{A}_d &amp;amp; - \mathbf{G} \end{bmatrix}$$ where $\mathbf{A}_i = \mathbf{W}_i \mathbf{A}$ for $\mathbf{W_i}$ random invertible matrices and $\mathbf{G}$ the gadget matrix of [MP12]&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.
We extend this to two new assumptions, the powerBASIS and PRISIS assumptions. Roughly, we introduce more structure in the $\mathbf{W}_i$. In powerBASIS, we let $\mathbf{W}_i = \mathbf{W}^{i}$, while in PRISIS we set $\mathbf{W}_i = w^{i} \mathbf{I}$.
With this added structure, the commitment scheme that we construct is exactly as in [WW23] (here we present the powerBASIS version).
Namely:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Setup}(1^\lambda) \to (\mathsf{pk}, \mathsf{vk})$ samples $\mathbf{A}, \mathbf{W}$ and uses [MP12]&lt;sup id="fnref1:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> sampling to construct a trapdoor $\mathbf{T}$ of $\mathbf{B}$. The verification key consists of $\mathbf{A}, \mathbf{W}$ and the proving key additionally contains $\mathbf{T}$.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Com}(\mathsf{pk}, f) \to (\sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ uses $\mathbf{T}$ to sample short $\mathbf{z_i}$ and $\hat{\mathbf{c}}$ such that $\mathbf{B}[\mathbf{z}_0, \dots, \mathbf{z}_d, \hat{\mathbf{c}}]^\top = [-f_0 \mathbf{W}^0 \mathbf{e}_1, \dots, - f_d \mathbf{W}^d \mathbf{e}_1]^\top$, it then outputs $\mathbf{c} := \mathbf{G}\hat{\mathbf{c}}$ and $(\mathbf{z}_i)$ as decommitment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>$\mathsf{Open}(\mathsf{vk}, f, \sigma, \mathsf{aux})$ checks that the openings are indeed short, and that the equations are all satisfied: namely it checks that $$\mathbf{A}\mathbf{z}_i + f_i \mathbf{e}_1 = \mathbf{W}^{-i}\mathbf{c} \enspace.$$&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We then show that this commitment scheme is binding (even with respect to relaxed openings, as customary in the lattice-world).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="evaluation-proofs">Evaluation Proofs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Now, our evaluation protocols are inspired partly by FRI (even though the setting and analysis are completely different). Suppose we aim to show that $f(u) = z$.
We take our polynomial $f$ and write it as an odd an even part i.e.:
$$f(X) = f_0(X^2) + Xf_1(X^2)$$
The prover then sends evaluations $z_0, z_1$ of $f_0, f_1$ on $u^2$.
The verifier checks that $z_0 + u z_1 = z$ and sends a random challenge $\alpha$ to the prover, and computes an updated commitment $\mathbf{c}&amp;rsquo; = (1 + \alpha \mathbf{W}^{-1}) \mathbf{c}$ and a new verification key where $\mathbf{W}&amp;rsquo; = \mathbf{W}^2$.
The prover computes a new folded polynomial $g$ and updated opening as follows:
$$g(X) = f_0(X) + \alpha f_1(X), \mathbf{s}_i = \mathbf{z}_{2i} + \alpha \mathbf{z}_{2i+1}\enspace.$$
The crucial observation is that the parties now can recurse on the claim that $g(u^2) = z_0 + \alpha z_1$, which is about a polynomial of degree $d/2$. We recurse thus $\log d$ times, until the prover can just send a constant sized opening.
Note in particular that the additional structure of the powerBASIS construction allowed the verifier to efficiently construct a commitment to $g$ from one to $f$. In particular, note that
$$\mathbf{A}\mathbf{s}_i + g_i \mathbf{e}_1 = \mathbf{A}\mathbf{z}_{2i} + f_{2i}\mathbf{e}_1 + \alpha \cdot ( \mathbf{A}\mathbf{z}_{2i+1} + f_{2i+1}\mathbf{e}_1)$$
$$ = \mathbf{W}^{-2i}\mathbf{c} + \alpha \mathbf{W}^{-2i - 1}\mathbf{c} = (\mathbf{W}^2)^{-i} (1 + \alpha \mathbf{W}^{-1})\mathbf{c}$$&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Crucially, compared to other protocols like lattice-bulletproofs, the extraction keeps the norm growth more manageable (at the cost of trusted setup), which should lead to more concretely efficient protocols. The details are in the paper, due to the requirement of a flurry of notation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, what is left to do is to manage the norm growth. We do this in two ways, which leads to two different protocols (with different tradeoff).&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>By selecting the challenge $\alpha$ to be a (signed) monomial, we can ensure that the norm (here and in extraction) remains polynomial throught the $\log d$ rounds of the protocol. This achieves a protocol with polylogarithmic communication and verifier complexity. However, since the challenge set is of size $\mathrm{poly}(\lambda)$, we obtain a non-negligible soundness error, which needs to be mitigated by parallel repetition, making the protocol unsuitable to be made non-interactive via Fiat-Shamir.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Instead of folding the polynomial halfway, we can aim to fold it in $k$-parts, and sample from an exponentially sized set. The norm growth is then much higher, only making it affordable to run the protocol $\log \log d$ iterations. Choosing $k$ appropriately, we are able to obtain a protocol with negligible knowledge soundness error and verifier and communication complexity &amp;ldquo;quasi-polylogarithmic&amp;rdquo; $d^{1/\log \log d}$&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="instantiations">Instantiations&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We then looked at how the scheme could perform concretely. The repetition needed to achieve 128 bits of security in the monomial protocol yields very large proof sizes, in the order of hundred of MBs. The other protocol strikes much closer to concrete efficiency, achieving proof sizes around 6 MBs.
We also looked at applying the two protocols in Marlin, making also use of some natural ways to aggregate our protocols. With this, we obtain a post-quantum zkSNARK for R1CS with proof size roughly 26 MBs. While this is still rather large, we are confident that further work will follow the asymptotic improvement to yield concretely efficient zkSNARKs from lattices.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="drawbacks">Drawbacks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We inherit many of the drawbacks of [WW23]&lt;sup id="fnref2:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>, namely:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The size of the proving key is quadratic in $d$.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We could not reduce powerBASIS (or original BASIS) to standard assumptions.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We require a trusted setup.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Furthermore, we our evaluations proof come with their own drawbacks:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The concrete proof sizes are rather large.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We could not achieve a fully polylogarithmic protocol with negligible soundness error.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>We are confident that these drawbacks can be overcome in future work (&lt;a class="link" href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/slap/" >wink 😉&lt;/a>).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Find the &lt;a class="link" href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2023/846" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>full version&lt;/a> for the gory details!&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1">
&lt;p>H. Wee and D. J. Wu. &amp;ldquo;Succinct Vector, Polynomial, and Functional Commitments from Lattices&amp;rdquo;. In: EUROCRYPT (3). Vol. 14006. Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Full version: &lt;a class="link" href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/1515" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://eprint.iacr.org/2022/1515&lt;/a>. Springer, 2023, pp. 385–416.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref1:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref2:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2">
&lt;p>A. Chiesa, Y. Hu, M. Maller, P. Mishra, N. Vesely, and N. Ward. &amp;ldquo;Marlin: Preprocessing zkSNARKs with Universal and Updatable SRS&amp;rdquo;. In: Proceedings of the 39th Annual International Conference on the Theory and Applications of Cryptographic Techniques. EUROCRYPT ’20. 2020, pp. 738–768.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3">
&lt;p>D. Micciancio and C. Peikert. &amp;ldquo;Trapdoors for Lattices: Simpler, Tighter, Faster, Smaller&amp;rdquo;. In: EUROCRYPT. 2012, pp. 700–718.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref1:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4">
&lt;p>We called this quasi-polylogarithmic because it roughly sits between sublinear ($d^{1/t}$ for $t$ a constant) and polylogarithmic $\mathrm{polylog}(d)$.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Publications</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/publications/publications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/publications/publications/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="2023">2023&lt;/h1>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>[AFON23] M. R. Albrecht, G. Fenzi, O. Lapiha, N. K. Nguyen. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>SLAP: Succinct Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments from Standard Assumptions&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;. Cryptology ePrint Archive, Paper 2023/1469. Available at: &lt;a class="link" href="https://ia.cr/2023/1469" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://ia.cr/2023/1469&lt;/a>. &lt;a class="link" href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/slap/" >Accompanying blog-post&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>[FN23] G. Fenzi, N. K. Nguyen. &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments: Towards Concrete and Asymptotical Efficiency&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;. Cryptology ePrint Archive, Paper 2023/846. Available at: &lt;a class="link" href="https://ia.cr/2023/846" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>https://ia.cr/2023/846&lt;/a>. &lt;a class="link" href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/" >Accompanying blog-post&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>