<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Lattices on Giacomo's Blog</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/</link><description>Recent content in Lattices on Giacomo's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 17:35:55 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>SLAP: Succinct Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments from Standard Assumptions</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/slap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 17:35:55 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/slap/</guid><description>Introduction This blog-post is a short introduction to our new work: &amp;ldquo;SLAP: Succinct Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments from Standard Assumptions&amp;rdquo;. This is joint work with Martin Albrecht, Oleksandra Lapiha and Ngoc Khanh Nguyen, and the full version is available on eprint.
In our previous paper, we looked at the problem of constructing efficient lattice-based polynomial commitments, to be used in as a drop-in replacement to non-post-quantum secure schemes such as KZG. In doing so we constructed two schemes making use of the techniques in [WW23]1 to obtain succinct verification and extractability.</description></item><item><title>Lattice-Based Polynomial Commitments: Towards Asymptotic and Concrete Efficiency</title><link>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Aug 2023 20:49:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://wizardofmenlo.github.io/lattices/towards-asymptotic-and-concrete-efficiency/</guid><description>Introduction In this blog-post, I will be taking a look at my recent work with Hossein Moghaddas and Ngoc Khanh Nguyen, full version. We extend the vector commitment scheme of [WW23]1 with an evaluation proof, and achieve a lattice-based polynomial commitment scheme with polylogarithmic proof size and verifier complexity. We further investigate the applicability of our techniques to the Polynomial IOP of [Marlin]2, show that our scheme is easily batchable and more!</description></item></channel></rss>